<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An aunsuuere made by Bar. Traheron to a priuie papiste vvhich crepte in to the English congregation of Christian exiles vndre the visor of a fauorer of the Gospel, but at lenghth bewraied himselfe to be one of the popes asses, thorough his slouche eares and than became a laughing stocke to al the companie, whom he had amased before with his maske : hereunto is added the subscription of the cheifest of the companie first, and afterward the subscriptio[n] of M. Ro. Watson ...</title>
            <author>Traheron, Bartholomew, 1510?-1558?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1558</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24167.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2369</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23347098</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23347098</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26558</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26558)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1804:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An aunsuuere made by Bar. Traheron to a priuie papiste vvhich crepte in to the English congregation of Christian exiles vndre the visor of a fauorer of the Gospel, but at lenghth bewraied himselfe to be one of the popes asses, thorough his slouche eares and than became a laughing stocke to al the companie, whom he had amased before with his maske : hereunto is added the subscription of the cheifest of the companie first, and afterward the subscriptio[n] of M. Ro. Watson ...</title>
                  <author>Traheron, Bartholomew, 1510?-1558?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[P.A. de Zuttere?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel?] imprinted :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1558.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁸.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Augustine, --  Saint, Bishop of Hippo. --  Enchiridion. --  English.</term>
               <term>God --  Will --  History of doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26558:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26558:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>AN AVNS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVERE MADE BY BAR, TRA<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>HERON TO A PRIVIE PAPISTE, vvhich crepte in to the engliſh congregation of chriſtian exiles vndre the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of a fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of the goſpel, but at lenghth bewraied himſelfe to be one of the popes aſſes, thorough his ſlouche ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, and than became a laughing ſtoc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to al the companie, whom he had amaſed before with his maſke. ¶Hereunto is added the ſubſcription of the cheifeſt of the companie firſt, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſubſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of M. Ro. Watſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, in ſpecial wordes, bicauſe he was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the beſt lerned amonge the reſt, &amp; therefore his iudgement was moſt regarded, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>¶Imprinted Anno. 1558.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26558:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26558:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>TO MASTER GIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> BARCKLEY.</head>
            <p>I Heard with great griefe of minde, how a countrefaite papiſte labored ſhame<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſly to deface your moſt honeſt, and godlie behauior towardes him, with the foule name of ſimuled frenſhip, &amp; flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And I know the tendernes of your herte, and how much it euer iuſtly grieueth you, that the good name, that god hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you, ſhuld be blemiſhed with falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes, &amp; impudent lies. But I truſt your wiſedom is ſuch, that you wil not be longe trobled, with the barckinges of ſo foule a mouthed maſtife. Wherefore I exhorte you to ſtaie your ſelfe againſt this open in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ground of an honeſt vpright co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, whereof ſondrie, that be here p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; haue longe time knowen you, giue vndoubted teſtimonies, &amp; haue ſeen moſt certaine frutes. This maſtife, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me I wil not vttre, though it ſignifie, that he came of a wilie generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hath opened his mouth againſt me alſo, and hath enfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced himſelfe to ſcratch, and teare me with his nailes. But god of his goodnes, hath giuen me alwaies, where with to defende
<pb facs="tcp:26558:3"/> my ſelfe. The defence that he hath now miniſtred vnto me, againſt this three hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Cerberus bred, &amp; longe fed in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes kennel, I dedicate to you my dere fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d maſter Barckley, bicauſe you haue ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned parte of this croſſe with me, and haue aſwel at this time, as at manie other ſtode ſo erneſtly in the defence of goddes truth, that you haue therefore prouoked a ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous tounge againſt you. God ſhal ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely requite you with his fauor, &amp; the lord Ieſus ſhal giue you a good reporte in the laſt daie. Praie for me, and ceaſe not to loue me, as I loue you, both for your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſingular good qualities, &amp; alſo for your honeſt godlie zeale, that you haue ſhewed in this matter. The lord Ieſus con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte you. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:26558:3"/>
            <p>THis ſentence of. S. Auguſt. I alleged to proue that al thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe bi goddes wil, and ordinance. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe be the great and moſt exquiſite worckes of god, that where as the nature of man, and angel had ſinned, that is to ſaie, had do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not that he wold, but that it wold, euen by the ſame wil of the creature, where by that was don, that the creator wold not, he fulfilled that he wold, vſing wel euen euil thinges, as good himſelfe in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gree, to the damnation of them, whom he iuſtly foreordained to puniſhment, and to the ſaluation of them, whom he merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foreordained to grace. For touching the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues thei did, that god wold not, but touching the omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of god, thei cold no waie do it. For euen in this that thei did againſt goddes wil, goddes wil was ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filled vpon them, or touching them. For therefore great, and exquiſite ar the lordes worckes thorough out al his wil, that after a meruailous, and vnſpeakable maner, that is not don beſides goddes wil, that is don a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt goddes wil. In Enchirid. ca. 120.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶TO THIS HERE FOLOVVETH MASTER MASKERS REPLICATION.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:26558:4"/>
               <p>SAint Aug. in the place by you alleged / ſpeaking of the great / <hi>&amp;</hi> exquiſite worc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes of god / ſaieth that whan the nature of angels / and man had ſinned / that is to ſaie / had don not that god wold / but that the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture wold / that he by the wil of the ſame creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / whereby was don that / which the creator wold not / might fulfille that he wold.</p>
               <p>Here haue you Saint Auguſtines ſentence in theſe few wordes al readie twiſe againſt your aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which is that it was the wil of god / that Adam ſhuld ſinne. For S. Auguſtine ſaieth that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan he ſinned / did not that god wold. And againe / did not that the creator wold. And if you yet vndreſtand not. S. Aug. to be manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly againſt you / than I counſel you / go to a logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian / and aſke of him / and he wil tel you / that your aſſertion / which is / that it was the wil of god / that Adam ſhuld ſinne / and S. Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes cenſure / which is / that man / whan he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / did not that god wold / be <hi>oppoſita con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria,</hi> which ſtriue ſo ſore / that thei can not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to gether, but the one ouerthroweth the other.</p>
               <p>Further to make the matter more euident / S. Aug. ſaieth / that as pertaininge to them / that is to ſaie angel / and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / thei did that god wold not / but as to the o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nipotentie of god / thei cold in no wiſe ſo haue do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / that is to ſaie haue ſinned
<pb facs="tcp:26558:4"/> againſt the wil of god / which. S. Auguſt. by <hi>&amp;</hi> by interpreteth / that it was the wil of god to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fre them to ſinne. Hitherto maſter Maſker. And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wordes of. S. Auguſt. that is not do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſides goddes wil / that is don againſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wil / this wiſe doctor maketh this gloſſe. That which is do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the wil of god / ys yet not don beſides his wil / that is to ſaie in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶HERE VPON I SENT HIM THIS LETTRE.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>BYcauſe you handle the place of Sainct Aug. bi me alleged, after ſuch ſorte, as you had neuer red anie other ſentence in him, I wil deſire you to read, and to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer theſe few places more ouer. Theſe be. S. Aug. wordes in the. 3. bo. de trinitate. Nothing is don, that procedeth not out of the inward, &amp; intelligible courte of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine emperour, according to his vnſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>akable iuſtice. For where doeth not the wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of almightie god worcke that he wil, which reacheth from ende to ende ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and diſpoſeth al thinges ſwetely. Agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. S. Aug. hath theſe wordes: It is than this wil only, from which is ſprounge, what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:26558:5"/> is. Item, Nothinge ſet in mannes free wil, ouerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth the wil of god, &amp; though man do againſt goddes wil, yet againſt his wil, which is him ſelfe, we ought to thincke nothing to be ſo do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as though he wold ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it to be don, and it is not don, or that he wold not haue to be don, and it is don. For that wil is euer fulfilled, ether touching vs, or of vs. Touching vs, it is fulfilled, but we fulfille it not, whan we ſinne. Of vs it is fulfilled, whan we do good. Item, ſo of man alſo god euer fulfilleth his wil, for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeth nothinge, whereof god worcketh not, that he wil. Item, goddes wil is the neceſſitee of al thinges. I cold allege in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable ſuch places, but that it is pitie, to combre ſo ſlendre a doctor, with to manie places at once. If you had ben aſmuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in reading. S. Au. as you haue ben oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupied in dreaming vaine victories to your ſelfe, in doting after glorie, and in making your ſelfe droncken, whith the ſwetenes thereof, you ſhuld haue knowen, that this is a principal propoſition in. S. Aug. which to proue, he driueth his argumentes. But you haue ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſo much time in kiſſing your faire daughter vaine glorie, that you haue had no leaſure, to know what Saint Aug.
<pb facs="tcp:26558:5"/> goeth aboute. Surely maſter. N. if you were not to be pitied bicauſe of your mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, you were wel to be laughed at, bicauſe of your fondnes. But I thincke it rather my dutie, to lament your moſt miſerable ſtate. But this I wil ſaie, that if you amend not your maners in time, you ſhal giue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſion, to bewraie your longe eares.</p>
                     <p>And than though you haue longe walked, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leo cumanus, it wilbe knowen what you be in dede. I wold be lothe to make a farther anatomie of your foule inwarde partes, but if I ſhal perceaue, that it ſhalbe to your welth, I wil not ſticke to giue you a launch, or two. I haue hitherto handled you a great deale more honeſtly, than you deſerue, for ſuch reſpectes, as god knoweth, and I haue labored to couer manie an il fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored ſpotte, but if you go forth in your wickednes, I wil ſtrippe you ſtarke na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſhew your ſcabbes to the world. God almightie vouchſafe to driue out that perte ſpirite, that combreth you. Amen.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>¶To this lettre maſter Maſker au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red firſt, that he wold differ the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwere to theſe places of. S. Aug. vntil I had aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his former interpretation vpon. S. Au.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26558:6"/>
               <head>Secondly that I fal to to raging, and that I can not iuſtly charge him with fondnes &amp; madnes. Thirdly he coniureth me to ſhew him his ſcabbes of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitee, if I know anie in him &amp;c. Whereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re foloweth my aunſwere.</head>
               <p>SIth the places, that I ſent you out of. S. Aug. plainly proue your vndreſtanding of S. Aug. to be extremely fond, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dotage, it is a ſhameles ſhift of you maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Maſker to ſaie, you wil differ the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, vntil I haue aunſwered your interp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation wrounge, &amp; wreſted not only with violence, but alſo with ſome loſſe of an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt conſcience. Wold you haue a better interpreter of S. Auguſt. than S. Aug. is him ſelfe? Make firſt S. Auguſtines declaration agree with your interpretation, &amp; tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal ſee, what I can ſaie farther. But bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you preſſe me, to ſaie ſomewhat to your interpretation, firſt you ſhal vndre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that I wot not, whether I maie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to ignorance, or to a gauled conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, that you haue falſly engliſſhed S. Aug. wordes. For, etiam per eandem creaturae
<pb facs="tcp:26558:6"/> voluntatem, that is to ſaie, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the ſame wil of the creature, you haue turned in to theſe wordes, by the wil of the ſame creatu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. Which chaunge of the word, the ſame, diminiſheth the weight of the ſentence. But vpon this hole ſentence of S. Aug. wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue wel rubbed your forehead, you ſaie, that S. Aug. is twiſe againſt me. For I ſaie, that it was goddes wil, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ſinne, and S. Aug. ſaieth, that man, whan he ſinned, did that god wold not. But to ſaie, that it was goddes wil, that man ſhuld ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and that man in ſinning, did that god wold not, be oppoſita contraria. I au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer that if a logicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil tel me ſo,, I wil tel him that he is an aſſe. For theſe two, as you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſtand them, be not oppoſita contraria as heate, and cold, but thei be contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, as this, maſter Maſter is vnlerned, &amp; m. Maſker is not vnlerned. And than if Saint Aug. be againſt vs, he ſpeaketh contradicto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ria. For he ſaieth, that by the ſame wil, whereby that was don, that god wold not, god fulfilled that he wold. If god fulfilled that he wold, by Adams ſinne, than was it plainly goddes wil, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ſinne. Or els god fulfilled his wil by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; not vpon his infallible purpoſe faſt grounded
<pb facs="tcp:26558:7"/> aeternally before, but ſuſpended his deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, &amp; kepte it vncertaine vpon Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doinge, and Adam might haue turned, and chaunged the hole matter. And if S. Aug. ſaie, that Adam did not that god wold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your meaning, than he ſpeaketh contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictorie ſentences, whereof the one muſt euer ouerthrow the other. But theſe two, be nether oppoſita contraria, nor contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictoria, as you vnlernedly affirme. For this worde, wil, is not taken in one ſenſe, in bothe places. For whan S Aug ſaieth in the firſt place, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did that god wold not, he meaneth that Adam did, that god alowed not in it ſelfe, and for it ſelfe. And whan he ſaieth, that god by the ſame wil of Adam, fulfilled that he wold, he meaneth that he fulfilled the thinge, that he purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, decreed, and ordained. For that S. Aug. ment that it was goddes wil, that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſhuld ſinne, theſe wordes ſignifie plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, to al them, that ar not quite paſt ſhame: Nothing is don, that procedeth not out of the inward courte of the ſoueraine empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror &amp;c. And the reſt of the ſentences, that I ſent you before declare the ſame moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently. But you go forth as wiſely, &amp; as honeſtly, as you beganne. For theſe
<pb facs="tcp:26558:7"/> wordes of S. Aug. Hoc quippe ipſo, quod co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei fecerunt, de ipſis facta eſt dei voluntas, you tranſlate thus: In that thei did againſt the wil of god, of them was don the wil of god. Firſt you ſlenderly turne, hoc quippe ipſo, that is to ſaie, in this verie thing it ſelfe, in to this, in that thei did, leauing out the emphaſis, and force of the ſpeech. And theſe wordes: De ipſis facta eſt voluntas Dei, you tranſlate, of them was don goddes wil, which tranſlation maketh the ſentence doubteful, whether we ſhal vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreſtande, that thei did goddes wil, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther god did his wil touchinge them. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re as the later ſenſe only, is S. Auguſti. mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Once more I aſke you, whether I ſhal aſcribe this to want of lerning, or to wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of honeſtie. But I praie you ſir, he that ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that goddes wil was fulfilled in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſinne of Adam, meaneth he not, that it was goddes wil, that Adam ſhuld ſinne?</p>
               <p>And whan you ſaie afterwarde, that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and Adam cold not haue ſinned agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the wil of god, wil not your peuiſh pride ſuffre you to perceaue, that ſo you graunt a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt your ſelfe, that it was goddes wil that thei ſhuld ſinne? For al other men ſee, that what ſoeuer is not don againſt goddes wil,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:8"/> is don with his wil. For you can not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke god to ſitte as a neuter, enclining to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parte. But how preatie is this, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re S. Aug. ſaieth, that, that is not don beſides goddes wil, that is don againſt his wil, you interprete, that S. Auguſt. meaneth, that it is not don beſides goddes wil in ſuffring. So manie thinges ar not don beſides maſter Maſkers wil in ſuffringe, where withal yet maſter Maſker hath nothing to do. But we ſaie, that nothing is do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſides goddes wil in ordaining, and ordring. For S. Aug. ſo exponeth him ſelfe in theſe wordes. For if this were not good, that euil thinges alſo ſhuld be, thei ſhuld in no wiſe be ſuffred of that almightie good, that is to ſaie, god. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without doubte, as eaſie as it is, to do what he wil, ſo eaſie is it not to ſuffre, that he wil not to be don. By theſe wordes it appeareth, that S. Auguſtines meaning is, that god ſuffreth nothinge, but that he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and ordaineth to be don. And than I ſend you this ſyllogiſme, what ſoeuer god ſuffreth to be don, he willeth, and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be don, after S. Auguſti. meaning, but god ſuffred Adam to ſinne, as no great ſainte maſter Maſker grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth, ergo it was goddes wil, and ordinance, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:26558:8"/> ſinne, after S. Aug. meaning. And than no greate ſainte maſter Maſker hath troubled this companie, without cauſe, to his awne ſhame. Take to you this ſyllogiſme alſo: Al the good thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, ar don by goddes wil, and ordinance, but it is good that euil thinges ſhuld be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world, as S. Aug. teacheth, ergo euil thinges ar don in the world, by goddes wil, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. Can you ſaie gentle brother, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out red cheekes, that nothing is don beſides goddes wil, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained by the wordes of S. Aug., and yet denie that it was goddes wil, that Adam ſhuld ſinne? Who wil tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke that you ar at home, whan you ſpeake? But now that I haue ſhewed you, your wilful blindnes, and groſſe ignorance in interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting S. Aug. I wil peruſe more of your let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre. You ſaie that I fal to raging. But you ſhal finde in the ende, that it was a good ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt zele vttered only to amende your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious faultes. You ar angrie that I char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge you with madnes, &amp; fondnes, for you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſee them, in your propre perſon. But if you cal to remembrance your whole be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauior in this only matter, that of late you haue enterpriſed amonge vs, you ſhal find more madnes, &amp; fondnes, than can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.
<pb facs="tcp:26558:9"/> And though you perchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce can not find it, bicauſe you be blinded with ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe loue, yet al other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue marked it, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re than maketh for your honeſtie. You ar not aſhamed to ſaie, that you offred a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for reconciliation, which in dede con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth nothing but ſhameles vaunting of your ſelfe, defacing of other far honeſter than you, railinges, malitious ſlaunders, &amp; open lies. And yet you can not ſee, wherein you haue broken charitee. Was not that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie charitably don of you, ſo gredely, and ſo malitiouſly to deſire, that M. Roſe might be puniſhed, a man that hath trauailed ſo long, ſo painfully, and ſo frutefully in the miniſterie of goddes worde, only bicauſe he rubbed your gauled backe, in telling you the truthe? Was not that verie charitably don of you, to defame that right godlie ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre man, maſter Barckley, with moſt deſpite<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, and ſhameles lies? Was not that verie charitably don of you to accuſe, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne the hole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie of hypocrital praiyng to god, beſides your ſelfe, the greateſt hypo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crite of al? Was not that verie charitably don of you to vttre ſuch a maſſe of poiſon againſt good men, whan you ſhuld haue p<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared your ſelfe to haue receaued the holie
<pb facs="tcp:26558:9"/> communion with them, if you had not ben a ſecrete papiſte, &amp; an vngodlie man. Wo worth ſuch charitee as might haue ſtaied ſo godlie a purpoſe, if god had not wrought more ſtrongly for vertue, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diuel cold worcke miſcheuouſly for vice. But now bicauſe you coniure me, to ſhew what ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes of iniquitie I know in you, I wil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge my conſcience. Firſt I ſaie that you ar a viſored, and diſguiſed papiſt, as you haue plainly enough diſcouered your ſelfe. Secondly I ſaie, that I ſee in you a proud, ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogant, contentious, vnquiet, and enuious ſpirite, which I praie god moſt hertely, to chaſe out of you, that we maie embrace you againe as a brother, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now we haue iuſt cauſe to abhorre, as a man voide of goddes feare, &amp; ſtuffed with manie horrible vices, beſides your ſubtil ſecrete papiſtrie. This vncleane ſpirite that I ſpeake of, and know to be in you, is the verie cauſe I am ſure, why you diſſente from vs in this queſtion of goddes prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For thorough god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des grace we haue not ben obſcure, nor per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plexed in this matter, nether can you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende ignorance. Enuie, and the loue that ſtil remaineth in you to your old harlotte poperie, hath moued you to ſtirre theſe coa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les.
<pb facs="tcp:26558:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26558:10"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26558:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26558:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26558:12"/> Let the feare of god, and loue of truth moue you againe to quench the fier that you haue kendled, or ſurely there ſhalbe a fier kendled in your herte that no man, nor time ſhal quenche. But I truſt you wil calle to god for a better minde. And to that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de I wrote before, and now write to you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. And I paſſe not though I ſeme to you to rage, ſo I maie bring you from verie raging in dede, and mere madnes. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re you faine, that I wold draw you, from re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pliyng againſt me with threates, that proce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth from your old diſeaſe. For I know by that, that you haue written alreadie, that you can ſaie nothing to the purpoſe againſt me. Yea if I were dèirous of glorie I wold deſire you to replie, that you might vttre more follie, which I cold eaſely turne to my greater praiſe. For I am ſure that you can bring nothing, but that, a man of meane ler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning maie eaſely ouerthrow, &amp; ſo gette glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie. Wherefore I nede not let you, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie aſmuch as you can, ſo you wold do it without bitternes of mind, without furious paſſions, without vaine bragges, without obſtinate, &amp; wilful blindnes, without dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken affection to your old Ione ſyluer pinne of Rome, which ſome thinke a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal hard<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:26558:12"/> obtaine at your handes. Further I muſt deſire you to make leſſe ſophiſtical argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, than you haue don in your former writinges. For whan you ſaie, that it was the wil of him only that Adam ſhuld ſinne, which only of his malitious nature, &amp; pro: pre inclination, tempteth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſinne, you ſhal finde in ſophiſterie, that it is called pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titio principij. For no man wil graunt, that it was Satans wil only, &amp; that it cold be the wil of none other, but of him that deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in ſinne, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, onles he be as fonde, as you ar. And this I haue declared ſufficiently in my former au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer al readie publiſhed, againſt which you threa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten to driue your blind battle rammes.</p>
               <p>But I truſt your puſh ſhal only bruſe your ſelfe, &amp; neuer ſhake, nor moue me. For I thanke god I ſtand faſter, and vpon a ſurer grounde, than that ſo ſlender batterie can beate me doune. You haue another dow baack reaſon of like meale, which is this: he that willeth not the death of a ſinner, which is the reward, &amp; effecte of ſinne, willeth not that man ſhuld ſinne. I praie you how proue you that god willeth the death of no ſinner ſeing that S. Pau. ſaieth, that he hath veſſels prepared vnto deſtruction? Willeth
<pb facs="tcp:26558:13"/> not the death of thoſe, whom he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to deſtruction? Againe how childiſh ſophiſtrie is this: he that is the autor of life, willeth no ſinne, which is the cauſe of death. It ſemeth that you thincke, that god willeth no man to die. And than al men die beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des goddes wil. Which no man I dare ſaie wil affirme, onles he be ſtarcke mad. I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe you therefore, to leaue theſe toies of plaine franſie. God giue to you, and to me ſpeedie repentance of our faultes, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your eyes in this matter, as he hath vouch ſafed to open ours, that we maie together agree in the truthe, in vnfained humilitee, and in chriſtian loue, which chriſtian loue yet hath hir ſharpnes, &amp; wil bite the faultes, that wil not other wiſe be amended. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore at my handes you ſhal loke to haue your boiles lau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched, &amp; to haue corroſies &amp; ſmarting plaiſters laied vpon them, vntil thei be cured. Goddes ſpirite directe vs.</p>
               <p>¶ Bar. Traheron your frend aſſone as you can loue the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:26558:13"/>
               <head>¶TO THIS LETTRE OVR countrefaite proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſent me an au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſtuffed with an huge heape of railing wordes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon I wrote thus vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him againe.</head>
               <p>IF you be not ſore ſicke, and feoble, after ſo great thronges, and after your deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſuch a ſwarme of innumerable railing wordes, as it were of young diuels, you maie be matched with anie ſhe giaunt in the world in ſtrong, and luſtie trauail, &amp; in your faire happie childbed. It ſemeth to me, that in the middeſt of your rauinge traunce, you had a litle witte remaining.</p>
               <p>For whereas you deſpeared victorie in al other thinges, you thought you wold ouer comme at the leſt in railing, ſcoffing, &amp; tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And ſurely you haue brought your ſwete purpoſe to paſſe. For I yeld vnto you this noble victorie, &amp; hold vp my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. And bicauſe you haue a meruailous greedie hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, &amp; a thirſt vnquencheable for vaine glorie, you ſhal haue this praiſe at my ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des alſo, that you ar the the iolieſt ſcold, and the greateſt railer, that euer I heard, or ſhal eare I thinke. But ſhal I not thincke
<pb facs="tcp:26558:14"/> that you wold ſporte your ſelfe in plaie, &amp; refreſh your forworen witte with a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, pleaſant, frantike imagination, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you wrote in the beginni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of your luſtie lettre after that you had powred out at one belche more than halfe a douſen malitious railing wordes, that you were taught by S. Pet. not to rendre rebuke for rebuke. Thought you it ſo good a thinge to take a while a litle pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>time in your ioieous franſie, that you paſſed not how longe men ſhuld lawgh at your mad behauior afterwarde? But if I ſhuld medle with al your ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge prankes, &amp; with al your new follies, I ſhuld ſhew my ſelfe lit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le leſſe fond, than you ar. I wil therefore pike out here, and there, that I thincke maie combre a ſimple reader. Otherwiſe to ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e the truth, al your gaie ſtuffe is ſuch, as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might be better deſpiſed, than aunſwered In regard of the vnlerned, and to ſhew you your foule fete, while you glorie in your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cockes fethers I muſt do ſome what againſt myn awne iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; ſtoupe ſo to houg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your hammes behinde, that you ſhal be ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to halte in this matter. Bicauſe I ſaid tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you wreſted S. Au. not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly violently, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo with ſome loſſe of a good conſcience you permitte to your ſelfe to affirme, that
<pb facs="tcp:26558:14"/> plaie Antichriſtes parte, ſo proudly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, to haue a place in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes conſcience. But if I plaie Antichriſtes parte in iudging your conſcience by the manifeſt frutes the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof, whoſe parte plaie you, whan in your writinge, you iudge ſo often, that to be in my herte, whereof you neuer ſaw frute, nor ſparke, nor anie maner of likelihod, I tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke god? Wel I beleue ere it be long, you ſhal fele, whoſe parte you haue plaied. You be verie angrie that I doubted whether you vndreſtode S. Aug. wordes, and you wold haue me to impute the faulte of your tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, to want of diligent examination.</p>
               <p>For you had leuer al othet faultes ſhuld be found in you, than lacke of lerning. Wel I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tente for this once, that you ſhal wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe awaie one faulte with another, and that men ſhal rather compte you raſhe, &amp; to run<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne blind fold for haſt, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſo eaſie latine wordes. But you be ſo good a man than you wil teach me my grammer to: For you ſaie, I engliſſh impleret, he ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>filled. For thorough haſt to teach, you ſtic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke not to make a lie. For this is my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: Theſe be the great worckes of god &amp;c. that he fulfilled &amp;c. Where I make im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleret, the ſubiunctiue mode, and not the
<pb facs="tcp:26558:15"/> indicatiue mode, as you ether ſhameleſly, or vnlernedly affirme. You engliſſe the word, impleret, might fulfille, &amp; ſo might I to, if I wold haue ſhewed my ſelfe as ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, as you ar. For might fulfil, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſentence doubteful. For god might fulfille his wil, though he did not fulfille his wil. But S. Aug. ment not, to leaue the ſentence in ſuſpenſe, that god might fulfil his wil, &amp; did not, but he ment to teach cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainly, that he did fulfille his wil. And thus by turni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſubiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctiue mode in to the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tential, you haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great paines, to ſhew your ſelfe as ignorant in grammer, as you did before, and do afterward in logike.</p>
               <p>Where I ſaid that S. Aug. meaneth, that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam did, that god wold not in it ſelfe, and for it ſelfe, bicauſe you can not confute it, you wold auoide it with a meruailous prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie ſhift. For you aunſwrr, that if it might be permitted to you, ſo to wreſt euerie au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, you wold haue none againſt you, &amp; that I affirme myn vndreſtanding only vpon a lordly autorite. Howbeit if you haue lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be at home a litle while, you ſhal vndreſtand, that I affirme not my ſaiynge, vpon myne awne autoritee, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a good ground. For if you denie that, or the like
<pb facs="tcp:26558:15"/> to be S. Au. meaning, you ſhal make him to ſpeak, not oppoſita co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traria, as you vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly powre out your wordes at auenture, but plaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictorie ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, &amp; to fighte againſt him ſelfe. But now at the laſt you ſhew an high point of wit, and lerninge.</p>
               <p>For where I proued that it was S. Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes minde, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinned by goddes wil, and ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, out of theſe his wordes: No thinge is don &amp;c., and out of the other ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tences alleged before, you ſaie that none of thoſe places, proue the matter. For, ſaie you, al thoſe places ſpeake of goddes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, whereby al thinges haue their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ar gouerned. If al thinges be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by goddes prouidence, as you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, than ſinful actes ar gouerned by his prouidence alſo, &amp; comme not to paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his wil, and ordinance. And what a preatie argument of yours is this, ſinne is a deprauation of nature, and the abſence of righteouſnes, ergo it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe by the ordinance of god. But, I wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, that the Iues committed in procuryng of Chriſtes death, was a deprauation of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, and and an abſence of righteouſnes, &amp; yet goddes hand foreordained it to be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the ſcripture teſtifieth. If you had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:26558:16"/> your argument thus, ſinne is a depraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of nature, ergo god is not the autor, nor propre worcker of it, you ſhuld haue ben heard, and alowed. For it is not al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to ordaine ſinne, and to be the autor of ſinne, as you in your dreame make them al one, whan you wot not what you ſpeake. But I muſt go farther, &amp; firſt telle you that ſondrie other of your aunſweres folowing ar nothing els but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> pythagoraes he ſpake it, which anie reader maie eaſely eſpie by him ſelfe. And bicauſe your auto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie with me is as great, as the popes mules maieſtie, I muſt telle you moreouer that, I wil ſpend no time aboute your naked affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. But it is a ſporte to ſee how clere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly you teach me logike. I aſked you this queſtion: he that ſaieth, that Adams ſinne was not don beſides goddes wil, meaneth he not, that it was don by goddes wil? To this you ſaie, that my queſtion pretendeth a ſimple conuerſion, &amp; bicauſe you doubte whether euer I red logike, you voucheſafe gently to teach me what a ſimple conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requireth. But your lucke is euer vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie. For while you labor to ſhew your ſelfe conning, you ſhew that you haue loſt your witte, and al lerning to. I haue red
<pb facs="tcp:26558:16"/> diligently though you frette more, than I wold wiſhe for enuie, the beſt autors, that write of logike. And thei teach, that their be three maners of conuerſions. The firſt is called conuerſio ſimplex. And that is, whan the ſame ſignes, and the ſame quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te remaining, the predicate is turned in to the ſubiecte, and the ſubiecte in to the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dicate. And this chaunge is made only in an vniuerſal negatiue, &amp; a particular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue. I muſt vſe of force logike ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, with a logician. The exemple of an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vniuerſal negatiue is this: Noman that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth god, abhorreth the readi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, ergo noman that abhorreth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſcripture, loueth god. Of a par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticular affirmatiue this maie be an exe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: Some raging paſſion in a mannes herte, is anger, ergo ſome anger is a raging paſſion.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde conuerſion is called con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſio per accidens. And that is, whan the ſubiecte is made of the predicate, and the predicate of the ſubiecte, the ſame qualite remaining, but the ſignes chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, that is to ſaie, the vniuerſal turned in to a particular thus: Euerie good thing is profitable, ergo ſome profitable thinge is good. The third is called conuerſio per contrapoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:17"/> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſubiecte is made of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate, and the predicate of the ſubiecte, ſo that by the remouing of the predicate, the ſubiecte is remoued, as what ſo euer is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, is honeſt, ergo what ſo euer is not honeſt, is not profitable. Now let a logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian ſhew me in what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion my quaeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is: he that ſaieth, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſinne was not don beſides goddes wil, ſaieth, that it was don by goddes wil. My ſcolemaſter ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth it is in a ſimple conuerſion. But here the ſubiecte is not turned in to the predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, nor the predicate in to the ſubiecte, but a declaration only is made, that, not beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des goddes wil, and by goddes wil is al one.</p>
               <p>And this had ben a ſimple conuerſion: Adams ſinne was not don beſides goddes wil, and goddes wil was not don beſides A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dams ſinne. Wherefore ſeing that in my queſtion there is no ſimple conuerſion, my maſter, affirming it ſo to be, is a verie ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple logician. But he ſaieth moreouer, that I ſhuld haue put the queſtion thus, he that ſaieth that Adams ſinne was not don beſides goddes wil, meaneth he not, that A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam ſinned, not beſides goddes wil. Now this is the ſonge of a couckoo, a tautologie, and vaine repetition of the ſelfe ſame thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:17"/> or it importeth, that the ſpeeches be of one force, and ſignifie the ſame thing after my meaning. Who ſeeth not now that god hath ſent ſuch a ſwimming in to this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle hed, that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knoweth not what he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proueth, dut confirmeth his aduerſaries ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng, while he wold ouerthrow it. Let vs procede, to this my ſyllogiſme. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer god ſuffreth to be don, he willeth &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daineth to be don, after S. Auguſtines mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, but god ſuffred Adam to ſinne, as no great ſaincte m. Maſker graunteth, ergo it was goddes wil, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ſinne, this diſguiſed popely perſon, ſaieth that the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ior, and the concluſion be falſe. But I wil proue the maior to be true, and than I truſt he wil not ſticke to graunte the concluſion to be true. For I am ſure that he wil find no fault in the minor, bicauſe it is his awne. S. Aug. ſaieth, that god ſuffreth nothing, but by iuſt iudgement, and that he ſuffreth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnwilling. If god ſuffre nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his iuſt iudgement, and his wil, who ſeeth not, that whatſoeuer god ſuffreth, he willeth, and ordaineth to be don, by his iuſt iudgement. For ſhewe me a thinge, that he willeth to be don in the world, and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore is don in the world, &amp; yet he ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:26558:18"/> it not to be don? For the ſcripture ſaieth, that what ſoeuer he wold, he hath don in heauen, and in erth. And he hath not brought anie thinge ro paſſe in the world, beſides his ordinance. And S. Aug. ſaieth, that this ſentence of the ſcipture ſhuld not be true, if god wold haue anie thinge to be don, and neuertheles hath not don it. But this new ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t dareth affirme, that god wold that Adam ſhuld not haue ſinned, and yet brought it not to paſſe, and ſo ouermala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertly, or rather blaſphemouſly ere he be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ware, he accuſeth the holie goſt, &amp; good S. Aug. of vntruthe. But now I muſt heare his worthie ſyllogiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bar. Taheron ſaieth / that it was goddes wil and ordinance / that Adam ſhuld ſinne / but the worde of god / and S. Aug. ſaie cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie / ergo Bar. Traheron lieth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I aunſwer that my maſter with another lie ſaieth that I lie, bicauſe his minor is ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meleſly falſe. For nether the word of god, nor S. Aug. is againſt my ſaiyng, but bothe make moſt plainly with it. The trial whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reof I permitte to the godlie. As for the preatie plaies, wherein he to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bleth himſelfe afterwarde in his aunſwere, I haue diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before. The ſimilitude, which he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:26558:18"/> of a king, who perdoneth an offender according to his longe purpoſe before, for the loue he beareth to him, is verie poore as himſelfe calleth it, and as I maie adde to his awne ſaiyng, verie peuiſch to. For he ſaieth, that the king fulfilled his wil vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the man, and yet ordained not, that the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld offend. And than he thincketh, that he hath brought forth a meruailous mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre, after a great terrible cracke. But he muſt ſhew, that god hath no more to do in ruling mennes mindes, than a king hath in ruling the mindes of his ſubiectes, if he wil bring anie thing to the purpoſe. A tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral kinges power entreth not in to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hertes, nor directeth them, but Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaieth, that the herte of a king is in goddes hand, be it neuer ſo fierce, wild, &amp; violent, and that he turneth it whether ſoeuer he wil. And therefore we aſcribe vnto god a farther matter, than to perdon offences, according to his purpoſe, namely euen to ordaine al thinges that ar don in the world, &amp; to directe, not only mennes bodies, but alſo their mindes to what it ſemeth good to his vnſercheable wiſedom. And this the ſcripture teacheth ſo plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, that he muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des haue a face of woodde, that wil denie
<pb facs="tcp:26558:19"/> it. But after that this countrefaite hathe proprely plaied this much of his enterlude he goeth aboute to waſſhe an aethiopian, &amp; to purge him ſelfe of ſuch vices, as al men know to be in him, that know him. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his happe is ſuch, that euerie thing is the worſe for his handling. For the more he waſſheth, &amp; ſcoureth himſelfe, the fowler he ſemeth to al men. But I am werie of the vnpleaſant ſauor of that boxe, which I wiſch neuer more to be opened before me. As for his railinges vpon me, and good m. Barckley, we paſſe as much as we do by the barckinges of a curre. Wherefore I lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue al that, &amp; comme to our matter againe. He beleueth, that I haue belied thoſe gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at worthie lerned men, whom I named in my boke, and affirmed to be on my ſide. wherein he ſheweth himſelfe to be a man of leſſe reading, than I thought. But lette him read Zuinglius De prouidentia Dei, OEcolampadius commenta. vpon Eſaie, Mar. Bucere vpon the epiſt. to the Ro. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theres ſeruum arbitriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Petre Martyrs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. vpon the epiſt. to the Cor. Caluines Inſtitution, and aunſwer contra calumnias nebulonis cuiuſdam, and there he ſhal fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de this doctrine that I hold, more plainly
<pb facs="tcp:26558:19"/> taught, &amp; more ſtrongly confirmed, than I can teache, or confirme. Now al that fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in this iolie triumphant lettre, is a ſincke of ſuch filth, that I am faine to runne from it, and let him wallow in it him ſelfe alone, that he maie bragge, that noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> durſt ſette vpon him. As for me I had rather plaie the cowarde, and take me to my leg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, than to aſſaulte him in ſo vile and ſtinc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king a place, where I ſhuld be more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with carinous ſauors, than honored with the ouerthrow of myn aduerſarie. Wherefore he ſhal ſticke there ſtil for me, and ſinge triumphes to himſelfe alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶AFTER THIS LETTRE, THERE FOLOVVETH A REPLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to my boke, and former aunſweres made to certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cauillations, and thereto this is the reioinder.</head>
               <p>MY ſtoute aduerſaries replication co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth much ſuperfluous talke. But I wil draw al in to as much ſhortnes, as I can, and meddle only with thoſe poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> that haue ſome color, whereby the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple maie be begiled. Where I ſaid, that if this be an vnreuerent ſpeech to ſaie, that it was goddes wil and ordinance, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this is an vnreuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpeech, to ſaie, that it was goddes wil &amp; ordinance, that the Iues ſhuld crucifie Chriſt &amp;c. he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nieth my conſequent, like a great logicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; laboureth miſerably to find ſome thinge vnlike in theſe ſpeeches. And at the laſt he hath eſpied, that the ſcripture ſaies not that it was goddes wil, and ordinance, that the Iues ſhuld ſinne in crucifiyng Chriſt. But ô ſophiſter how cold god ordaine, that the Iues ſhuld crucifie Chriſt, ſo innocent a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without their ſinne? Wherefore he that ordained the Iues to crucifie Chriſt, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them to ſinne in crucifii<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Chriſt. And than I giue you this ſyllogiſme where vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to gnaw: Who ſo ordaineth a nawghtie man to kil a verie innocent, ordaineth him to ſinne, but god ordained the wicked Iues to kil Chriſt a moſt innocent blameles ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ergo he ordained them to ſinne. And ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> god was not the autor and propre worcke of the malitious crueltie, that was in the Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es, but ordained only, that the Iues ſhuld ſinne in vttering that crueltie of their awn
<pb facs="tcp:26558:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> hertes wrought of them ſelues, &amp; ſproung out of their awne corruption vpon his ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Chriſt, as I haue ſhewed in my boke, and wil ſhew more largely hereafter, whan I muſt bewraie how hedſtrong a beaſt this is, which wil not obeie the bridle, but ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil, and affirme, that to ordaine a thinge, &amp; to be the autor, &amp; propre worcker of a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, is al one. As for his follie in turning god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ordinance, which worde the ſcripture hath in this place, in to goddes bare ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, which word the ſcripture hath not, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiently vttered before. But ſee what a fowle fal this faire beaſt giueth himſelfe. For he writeth, that we can not ſaie, that god ſo ſuffered the Iues actes, that he had no doing, or medling therewith. For their bodies, and ſowles, ſaieth he, &amp; al the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſtirringes, &amp; motions of them, were of god &amp;c, Firſt if god had to do with their actes, I am ſure thei did nothing, whether he wold, or no. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly if al their ſtirrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; motions were of god, than that they ſtirred, &amp; moued them ſelues agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt Chriſt, was of god. And how that cold be don without their ſinne, let this luſtie logician ſhew. And thus he teacheth, that it was of god, that the Iues ſinned againſt Chriſt.
<pb facs="tcp:26558:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> For we ſpeake not of ſtirring, and mouing ſimply, but of ſtirring and mouing againſt Chriſt, which is ſinne. Howbeit I vſe not that ſpeech, that the Iues ſinning againſt Chriſt, was of god, not that it maie no waie be ſuffered, but bicauſe that it maie ſeme to ſignifie, that god was the autor, &amp; propre worcker of their ſinning, which is horribly falſe. But I ſaie that their ſinning was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and ordred by god. For god or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that thei, after that ſorte, ſhuld vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre the ſinnes, that lurcked in their hertes, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitte moſt wicked actes agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt Chriſt</p>
               <p>This Polyphemus than hath not yet hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led his wounded forehed, but in ſaluing of it, hath made it worſe. I alleged this pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Salomon, god hath wrought al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for him ſelfe, to proue that the world is gouerned, by goddes prouidence, and tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nothing commeth to paſſe, beſides his ord<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nance. To this our noble aduerſarie repli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth, with theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who denieth that god wrought al thinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for him ſelfe / but what maketh that to proue that it was goddes wil / and ordinance / that A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam ſhuld ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſemeth that this famous clercke, thinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that Salomon ſpeaketh of goddes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:26558:21"/> of creatures, as though his worde were bara, or aſa, or iatſer, but his worde is paal, and he vſeth it, in that ſenſe, wherein it is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the pſal. 44. our fathers haue tolde vs, poal paaltha, the worcke that thou wrough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt in their daies. Salomon than ſpeaketh of goddes prouidence, in directing and go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerning al the actes, that comme to paſſe in the world to his glorie. And than I ſaie, that if it be ſo that goddes prouidence is ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tended thorough out al mennes doinges, than Adam ſinned not beſides his wil, &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinance. But how like himſelfe is this doughtie wight, whan he maketh this great reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinne is a priuation / and abſence of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes / ergo it camme not to paſſe by goddes wil / and ordinance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For who knoweth not, that darcknes is a priuation, &amp; abſence of light? &amp; yet who ſo ſhal ſaie, that darcknes camme to paſſe beſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des goddes wil, and ordinance, ſhalbe hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of the companie of al chriſtians, and driuen home againe to the popes poiſoned puddel, or to Epicures ſwines ſtie. Where Salomon ſaieth, that god hath wrought the vngodlie to an euil daie, our ſolemne diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſaieth, that god wrought in the generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> and begetting of the wicked, &amp; left him in the ſtate of perdition, that he contracted of his parentes. But Salomons meaning is, that god hath ordained the wicked to da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for his awne glorie, in ſetting forth his righteouſnes, as it is knowen almoſt to euerie barber. Whan Ieremie aſketh this queſtion: who is he that ſaieth, a thinge is don, and the lord commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it not, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to them, that haue anie ſkille in the hebrue tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, aſmuch as if he had ſaid, who is he, that ſaieth, that anie thinge is don, and the lord ordained it not. This ſentence our giaunt violently cruſſheth together, &amp; reſtraineth only to plages, and puniſchmen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. But I wil know, who gaue him auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, to curtal large ſentences, and to turne euerie thing, in to ſome thing before I yeld to his tyrannie. In the expoſition of the ſeconde place of Ieremie, which I alleged to proue, that goddes prouidence reacheth to the directing of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes doinges, he grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that god vſed the furie, and malice of the diuel, &amp; of the kinge of Babilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſch his people, and yet he wil not graunt, that he ordaineth mennes ſinnes. And no meruail, for thei that ſpeake in a franſie, ſtic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke not to ſpeake thinges fightinge with them
<pb facs="tcp:26558:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſelues. For thei know not what thei ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. He laboreth afterwarde to ſhew, that the kinge of Babilons ſinne camme of his aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne corrupte inclination, and not of god, as though I had not made it plaine before, that though god vſe, and ordaine mennes ſinnes to his glorie, yet he is not the autor &amp; propre worcker of them. To the place of Salomon, concerning the gouerna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of lot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; to the place of Eſaie, where god tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs that he frameth &amp;c. Theſe be his wordes for aunſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe places manifeſtly proue / that al thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ar wrought / and gouerned by goddes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence. And who denieth that? But what is this to proue / that it was goddes wil / that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſhuld ſinne / which came of the malice of the deuel / and Adams vncleane luſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hitherto this ſicke man. For he muſt be verie ſicke, that ſaieth, that al thinges ar wrought, and gouerned by goddes proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and yet holdeth that ſinnes ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the world beſides his wil, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. He muſt be alſo ſome what il at ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe in his braine, that maketh this argument, ſinne camme of the malice of the diuel &amp; mannes luſt, ergo it was not ordained by god. For god ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; doeth ordaine thinges
<pb facs="tcp:26558:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> whereof the diuel, and mannes nawghtie herte, be the autors, verie cauſes, &amp; propre worckers, as I thinke we haue now made ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt to euerie childe. But heare farther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If you wil ſaie / ſaieth he / that goddes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence ſo ruled / and turned Adams ſinne / that he made it to ſerue his glorie / than ſhal you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſtand theſe places rightly / and tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wil ſaie with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely ſir, you know wel enough, that I haue ſo ſaide, &amp; written more than twiſe, or thriſe, &amp; ſo haue you graunted againſt your wil, and to the loſſe of your ſore tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, that I haue rightly vndreſtanded tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe places of the ſcripture, and ſo muſt you yeld to me in this matter, if you be be an ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſt man of your word. But ſome feare you wil ſaie rather that you ſpake al this in a traunce, or in a ſodaine paſſion, or that for lacke of leaſure, you examined not wel your writinges. But how can you ſaie, that god determined before al time, to rule, &amp; gouerne Adams ſinne, and yet that Adam ſinned beſides goddes wil, and ordinance. For god doeth nothing, that he had not cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tainly purpoſed before al time. But he cold not certainly determine to rule, &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne Adams ſinne to his glorie, if Adam ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:26558:23"/> beſides his wil, and ordinance, and might for al his wil, &amp; ordinance haue not ſinned. After this our glorious champian commeth to the argument, that was made out of theſe wordes of Dauid, god willeth none iniquite, and graunteth without tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, that I haue taught the true meaning of the place, and ſo ouer turneth the reaſon, wherein he gloried ſo much before. But he falleth againe to his old groſſe error, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can wil nothing, wherein he delighteth not, which fondnes he might haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed in the later ende of my boke ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. And if he red that place, and yet wold ſticke ſtil in the ſame myre, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, that he had leuer be compted ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, than a man reformed. And ſo I fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re I ſhalbe faine to leaue him, onles god vouchſafe ſpeedely to ſhew his mightie hande. Where I ſaid that thei aſcribe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knes to god, that teach, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides goddes wil, &amp; whether god wold, or no, he auoideth it proprely with this only, that my ſimilitude aſcribeth weaknes to goddes wil. But though I had ſo ſlender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled the matter, as I thanke god I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not, yet he had not therefore auoided, but that he had aſcribed weaknes to god.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:26558:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Nether ſhuld he haue thought, that he had wel purged the more of his awne garmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, by caſting other like mire vpon mine. But let vs ſee how profoundly he perceth to the botome of darcknes to fetch vp this geare. To ſaie, that god willeth a thing, wherein he delighteth not for it ſelfe, he affirmeth to aſcribe weaknes to god. For we can not wil a thing, wherein we delight not, nor alow, but for eſchewing of greater inconuenience, which els we can in no wiſe auoide. Firſt marcke, that whereas he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed ſimply before, that we can not wil the thinge, that we delighte not in here I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not tel by what miſchaunce, he graunteth, that we maie wil a thinge, wherein we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light not, for the auoidance of a greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience. But I wil ſhortely ſhew that we maie wil a thinge for a certaine purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and not delighte in it, for it ſelfe, though we be not compelled thereunto thorough the daunger of a greater inconuenience, &amp; though we might auoide it. I praie you ô the leſt of the noble companie of Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and Dorbeles, maie I not wil, that you ſhal vttre your follie in writing, wherein I promiſe you, I delight not, for a certaine purpoſe, namely that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereafter maie
<pb facs="tcp:26558:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> runne in to the like madnes, though I cold otherwiſe auoide it, without the compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of neceſſitie? And albeit that I cold not bringe al this to paſſe, yet I know god cold bring it to paſſe, not thorough the weakenes of his wil, as you dreame, but thorough the mightines of his wil, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee that be awa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. Cold not god I praie you wil and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Satans miniſters, to robbe Iob, onles he delighted in their robberie for it ſelfe, or of neceſſitee to auoide a greater incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience? Cold not he wil, and ordaine Achabs falſe prophetes to lie, onles he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in their liyng for it ſelfe? Cold not he wil, and ordaine, that Hophnie, and Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neas ſhuld not heare their fathers good ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monition, bicauſe he wold kil them, onles he delighted in their ſtubburne diſobedien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, or of neceſſitee to auoid a greater incon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenience? God than willeth thinges, that he delighteth not in for them ſelues, nether by reaſon of weakenes, nor to auoide a grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter inconuenience, but to ſette forth before mennes eyes, his power, his wiſedom, his righteouſnes, his goodnes, and mercie. Which vertues yet neuer to be knowen to the world, we maie wel iudge to be an inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenience touching vs, but touching god, it is
<pb facs="tcp:26558:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> none at al. For he might haue remained perfectly bliſful in him ſelfe, though he had neuer made vs. Awaie than with this vaine iangling. But let vs ſe more of this gaie ſtuffe. Our preatie Polyphemus wil not confeſſe, that he goeth aboute to pulle god out of his throne. For ſaieth he, his office of gouerning, conſiſteth not in this, that it was his wil, &amp; ordinance, that Adam ſhuld ſinne. But if you take from god the ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, gouerning, and directing of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and of al mennes ſinnes, you ſhal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charch him of a great parte of his gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo farre like a young giaunt, you go furiouſly aboute, to pulle him out of his throne, to your awne deſtruction. But we ar demaunded an high quaeſtion, how we can proue that thei, which teach, that it was not goddes wil, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, do teach that thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whether god wil or no. I praie you maſter Doctor, he that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the thing, that you wold it ſhuld not be do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doeth he it not, whether you wil, or no? But you ſaie, that Adam ſinned not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther god wold or no, for god ſuffered him to ſinne. But that proueth not yet, but that Adam ſinned whether god wold, or no. For one maie ſuffre a thinge to be don,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> whether he wil or no. If you wil ſaie, that god ſuffred it willingly, than you graunt with vs, that it was his wil, that Adam ſhuld ſinne. And than you haue plaied the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of a verie honeſt wiſe man al this while. Where to myn aunſwere, that god teſtified to Adam by his commaundment, what he alowed, and what his pleaſure was, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie, that if god had willed, &amp; decreed, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld through his awne faulte, do the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which god had forbidden before, god ſhuld therein haue willed, and decreed, the commaundment that he gaue before to be broken, and than that had ben a contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, and repugnantie in him, I aunſwer that you haue more than ſerpentes eyes, if you ſee that contrarietee, and repugnantie.</p>
               <p>You maie wel dreame, that you ſee it in your ſleepe, but whan you awake, you ſhal perceaue, that it was but a vaine fanſie, &amp; a fliyng imagination. For maie not a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther laie vp apples in his chambre, and giue a commaundment to his children, that thei ſhal nor meddle with them, and yet wil, &amp; decree with him ſelfe as much as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maie wil, and decree, that thei ſhal ſteale them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie, and eate them, to this ende, that he maie ierke them wel, and thriftely, whereby
<pb facs="tcp:26558:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> while thei liue afterwarde, thei maie feare to ſteale, or to be lycorous, or to breake their fathers commaundment? Maie not I ſaie a father do al this, onles he be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and repugnant to him ſelfe? Much mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re cold god wil, &amp; decree, that Adam ſhuld breake his commaundment thorough his awne faulte, for a more excellent purpoſe, without contrarietee, &amp; repugnance in him ſelfe. Whan afterwarde you ſaie, that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſinning did not the wil of god, if by the word, wil, you meane goddes decree, you miſſe the cuſſhion, if by the word, wil, you meane that god alowed not Adams ſinne, ne had pleaſure in it, for the ſinne it ſelfe, I aſſente thereunto. But how haue you than proued that it was not god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des wil, decree, and ordinance, that Adam ſhuld ſinne? Againſt myn aunſwer to the fourth argument ſpoken of in my boke, you haue brought nothing worthie to be reher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed. Wherefore I paſſe ouer to myn aunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to the fift argument. Againſt him that obiected Adams fre wil, I ſaid that goddes wil, and ordinance, letted not, but that Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld do frely, and willingly without com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulſion, that he did. And how that might be, I ſhewed by exemples, which you touch
<pb facs="tcp:26558:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> not bicauſe thei were to hotte. But to that you replie, that I wringe Adams free wil al together on the lift hand, that is to ſinne, &amp; death, but I leaue not free wil to the right hand, that is to the keping of goddes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment, and aeternal life. I aunſwer that god made Adam in ſuch integritee, vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rightnes, &amp; perfection of nature, that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wold do goddes commaundmentes, he might do them frely, and willingly, &amp; haue abundant ſufficientie of natural ſtrenghth thereunto, and whan he wold decline from goddes commaundement, he might do the ſame frely, and willingly thorough his aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne faulte, and not thorough want of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtrength. And I ſaie that his fre wil ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in this vprightnes, ſtrength, &amp; perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature, &amp; not in choiſe of this, or that. For if there were no free wil, but where a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maie chooſe whether he wil do the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that is good, or the thinge that is euil, than there were no fre wil in god, whoſe wil is moſt free. For he can do no euil, but only the thinges that be good. Wherefore whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re thinges be don frely, and willingly, and wihout compulſion thorough no want of natural ſtrength, there is free wil ſaie I.</p>
               <p>And this I know was in Adam, but no ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:26558:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> fre wil, whereby he might diſappoint god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des certaine purpoſe, or whereby it ſhuld folow, that god had yet determined nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g certainly. But now though manie thinges powred out to no purpoſe folow in this re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication, I maie not paſſe ouer, that where I aſked, whether he wold ſaie this: Death came in to the world by the enuie of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, ergo it was not ordained by god, he au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth flatly, that death was not ordained by god. And allegeth a ſentence for him, out of the firſt of wiſedom. God made not death, nether hath he pleaſure in the deſtruction of the liuinge. To this I ſaie, that the autor of that boke, meaneth no mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re but that god was not the propre cauſe of death, but the diuels enuie, and mannes ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and yet it foloweth not but that god or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined death for mennes ſinne. For a king in his realme ordaineth hanginge for theues, and murtherers, and yet is not the propre cauſe of their hanging, but their aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nawghtines. And I ſaie once more that he that ſaieth, that god ordaineth not death for mennes ſinnes, ſaieth that men die beſides goddes ordinance. But this geare is to groſſe, where with farther to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre the reader. Now foloweth a worthie
<pb facs="tcp:26558:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> matter. I made this ſyllogiſme: whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer was in Adam, was in him by goddes wil, and ordinance, ſinne was in Adam, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go &amp;c. My ioilie chalenger denieth the maior of this ſyllogiſme. as though al the ſcriptures that I alleged before, &amp; S. Aug. ſentences, did not proue it to be infallibly true. But to ſaie that ſinne was in Adam by goddes wil, and ordinance, he affirmeth to be al one with this, god is the autor of ſinne, for he can not ſee how anie bodie can ordaine a thing, and not be the autor, head ſpring, cauſe, and propre worcker of it.</p>
               <p>And he laboreth to proue this by lame ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes, as though that if he cold proue it ſo in ſome thinges, he had by &amp; by proued it ſo in al thinges. Hereunto I aunſwere, that the ſcipture ſheweth plainly, that al the thinges, that be in man, be in him by goddes ordinance, and the ſame ſcripture ſheweth, as plainly that god is not the autor of ſinne. Wherefore to ordaine ſinne, and to be the autor of ſinne, is not al one. And that to ordaine a thinge, and to be the propre cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, autor, and worcker of a thinge, is not al one, theſe exemples maie teach the vnler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. He that ſetteth his wine abrode in the ſunne to be made vineger, ordaineth it to
<pb facs="tcp:26558:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> be made vineger, and yet he is not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre cauſe of vineger, but the nature of the wine, and the hote ſunne beames. Agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne he that in ſpaine cutteth dounne grapes, in the ſommer, and laieth them in a ſunnie place, ordaineth them to be made reaſines, &amp; yet he is not the propre cauſe of reaſines, but the nature of the grapes, and the heate of the ſunne. Finally to bringe a plaine ruſtical exemple, he that hangeth vp ſwines fleſh in a chimneie, ordaineth it to be made bacon, and yet he is not the propre cauſe of bacon, but the nature of the fleſch, and ſmo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. Wherefore ſith it is euident, that it is not euer al one, to ordaine a thinge, and to be the propre cauſe, and autor of a thinge, we maie boldly ſaie, the ſcripture bearinge plaine recorde, and S. Aug. and ſondrie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t writers holding vp their handes to the ſame, that god ordaineth ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and yet is not the autor of ſinne. How god ordained Adam to ſinne, thorough A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams awne faulte, and without al maner of faulte in god, I graunt in dede, that it is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de for weake wittes to vndreſtande, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles I am ſure, that it is moſt certai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly true. And ſo we ar al bounde to beleue, whether we vnderſtande it, or no, onles we wil flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:26558:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> and pleaſe our ſelues in a moſt open, &amp; a moſt dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous error. And if I wold ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluouſly ſpend wordes, I could eaſely ſhew, that the exemples, which my doctor bringeth to declare, that to ordaine, and to be the autor of a thing, is al one, proue not his purpoſe. For who knoweth not, that Solon was not the autor of the lawes, which he ordained amonge the Atheniens. For thoſe lawes were before in other commune weales, and cheyfely in the commune weale of the hebru., &amp; goddes wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dede is the autor of al good lawes, &amp; noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad. But the matter is to manifeſt of it ſelfe. And the reſt of the replication is mere tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feling. Where the ſcripture teacheth, that god bad the liyng ſpirite to go in to Ahabs prophetes, and to deceaue Ahab, he aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth, that god ſuffred the liyng ſpirite to go &amp;c. But he ſhuld haue ſhewed, that to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde a thinge to be don, is no more, but to ſuffre a thinge to be don. But I wil here preſent my doctor with this ſyllogiſme: he that commaunded the liynge ſpirite to go, and to make liers, commaunded him to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, but god commaunded him to go, &amp; to make falſe liyng prophetes, ergo he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to ſinne. But god commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth
<pb facs="tcp:26558:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> nothing, which he ordaineth not, ſo he ordai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned him to ſinne. And yet euerie ſtarcke foole maie ſee, that god was not the autor, &amp; propre worcker of the liyng ſpirites ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, but found it in him al readie wrought, thorough his awne corrupting of himſelfe, and iuſtly vſed it to puniſch that nawghtie man. And why, I praie you, ſhuld not god commaunde and ordaine a ſinful bodie to ſhew his nature, that is to ſaie, to ſinne? It is certaine by the teſtimonie of the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, that god commaundeth Satan to do ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie thinges, and I wold faine know how he can bid him to do anie thinge, &amp; not to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Wherefore he that biddeth him do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thinge, muſt nedes bidde him to ſinne. But ſeing that god commaundeth him to do manie thinges, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth nothing beſides his awne ordinance, it foloweth of neceſſitee, that god ordaineth ſinnes to be don, though he be not the autor, and propre worcker of ſinne. But let vs ſee more. He is angrie that I ſaid, that he turned al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des doinges in to ſufferinges. For he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, he turneth not al, but ſome. But than I ſaie, that he hath brought nothing againſt my ſentence, that it was goddes wil, and or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinance, that Adam ſhuld ſinne. For onles
<pb facs="tcp:26558:29"/> he can proue, that al goddes doinges be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fringes, I wil holde my ſentence ſtil in the nombre of thoſe thinges that ar don, &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by god, and not amonge thoſe, that be only ſuffred by god. And I wil not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fre my ſentence to go a ſtraw bredth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir place, vntil I ſee by what right he can remo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue hir. Touching goddes ſufferance, and how he ſuffreth nothinge beſides his wil, &amp; ordinance, and that his ſufferance is his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I haue ſufficiently declared before. Here I might make an ende, ſauing that my good honeſt fellow co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth, that I left three thinges of his vnaunſwered, where as in dede I left but one of them vnaunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; that was, for that I ſaw no cauſe why I ſhuld au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſwer it. And this is the gaie thing that muſt be aunſwered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your aſſertion ſimply vndreſtanded / ſaieth he / is plaine blaſphemie by your awne confeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Bicauſe I am driuen, and compelled, I aunſwere to this, that hitherto I neuer ſaid ſo in my life. And yet I denie not, but that it maie be ſo expouned, that it maie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teine blaſphemie, as if a man wold ſaie, whan I af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firme that it was goddes wil and ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, that god ordained Adam to ſinne, only bicauſe he delighted in
<pb facs="tcp:26558:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſinne, or for the ſinnes ſake alone, or as though god were the autor, &amp; propre wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of Adams ſinne. But I ſaie that ſuch an interpreter, and gloſer, ſhuld not only ſhew himſelfe a froward ouerthwart foole but alſo a ſhameles mad man. For I my ſelfe haue declared that, that is as far from my meaning, as hel is from heauen. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſtly pike it out of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Howbeit I know that there is nothing ſo wel ſpoken, that a peruerſe wranglinge wit can not by wreſting, &amp; wringing depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue. And here I wold make an ende of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe iuſtes, but firſt I am required to ſaie ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mewhat to the commune obiection, that is in the mouth of euerie pert peremonger, of euerie raſkal, and euerie rakehel. For thei bable, that if al thinges, comme to paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe according to goddes foreſight, prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and certaine vnmoued, and vnchaungea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble ordinance, than thei wil make no proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for meate, to ſatiſfiie their honger, thei wil vſe no medicine in their ſicknes, thei wil not procure to auoide anie daunger &amp;c. For the good thinges that god hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned For them, thei ſhal haue, &amp; the euil, that god hath appointed, thei can not eſchue. So that ether it ſhal not nede, or it ſhal not
<pb facs="tcp:26558:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> boote to labor for the obteining of the one or auoiding of the other, ſith al muſt be, as it is alreadie decreed, &amp; determined without alteration, and chaunge. But ô rude rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble what if god wil vſe your labor, and the wiſedom, and giftes wherewith he hath fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed you, to ſerue his prouidence, wil you refuſe to be his inſtrumentes with al that you haue of him? If it be his ordinance to fede you thorough your trauail, wil you lie gaping while meate falle in to your mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes out of the cloudes, which thing you per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue he hath not appointed? If it pleaſe him to heale you by the vertu, that he hath giuen to herbes, or ſpices, or other ſimples, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you wil not be ſo healed, I wold you ſhuld be ſicke ſtil. If he wil haue you to eſcape daungers thorough the wiſedom, and wari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, that he hath planted in your hertes, an you wil not vſe the ſame, you ar worthie to periſch in them, &amp; ſo god wil vſe your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to your iuſt deſtruction. The godlie euer like that wel, that pleaſeth god, nether wil thei ſhew them ſelues ether ſo vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or ſo foliſch, as to deſpice, or refuſe the meanes, that he hath appointed. And though thei know that nothing can comme to paſſe otherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ordained, yet
<pb facs="tcp:26558:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> they know not whether this waie, or that waie, by this meane, or that meane, he wil bringe his purpoſe to paſſe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thei vſe the meane with thanckes, that ſemeth moſt likelie, according to the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that god hath giuen them. For whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther god worcke thinges by him ſelfe, or by thoſe meanes &amp; inſtrumentes, that he hath appointed, al his one to them, and thei ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege his wiſedom, and goodnes aſwel in the one, as in the other. But yet theſe hogges gru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te more ſwiniſhly, that if al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges comme to paſſe by goddes prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, than robberies, adulteries, murders ar not don, but by goddes wil, and ordinance, and than why ar theues, adulterers, and murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers puniſched, ſith thei haue ſerued goddes wil &amp; prouidence. This filthie flocke muſt vndreſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that wicked men committe not their nawghtie vilainous actes to the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to ſerue goddes wil, but to ſatiſfie theyr awne luſtes. For he ſerueth goddes wil, that doeth the thinge, that god commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth him to do by his worde. But in what worde hath god commaunded anie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to committe adulterie &amp;c. But you wil ſaie if god had not determined, and ordained theſe thinges, thei ſhuld not come to paſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:26558:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> I graunt, for god vſeth mennes nawghtines to his glorie, and ſheweth his wiſedom in vttering mennes inwarde poiſoned affecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, and his righteouſnes in puniſhing one ſinne with another. But ar thei therefore not to be puniſhed, bicauſe god ordaineth, that thei ſhal bewraie their priuie filthines and abomination? Or do thei powre out &amp; ſhew abrode the wickednes of their her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to ſerue goddes wil, or their awne wil, and raging deſires? If it be plaine, that thei dotingly ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne after their awne vnbrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led luſtes, without al reſpecte of goddes wil, and commaundment, yea in contempt of god, and his worde, thei ar nether wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, nor ſhal eſcape goddes vengeance. And we maie not be now ſo foliſch, &amp; aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed as to thinke that god in ordaining mennes euil dedes is defiled therewith. For we haue ben taught often enough, that he is not the autor, and propre worcker of them. And therefore he remaineth euer pure himſelfe in bringing forth to light, &amp; in ordring that is vnpure in vs, and the filthi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes cleaueth vpon them only, that ar the propre worckers of euil, and not on him, who ordaineth wel, that men, &amp; diuels ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue wrought euil. But of this matter we
<pb facs="tcp:26558:32"/> haue ſpoken aſmuch, as maie ſuffice al ſuch, as ſeke rather to know the truth, than to wrangle, and ſhew eloquence in pratinge braulinge, and cauillinge.</p>
               <p>Now good reader thou ſhalt vndreſtand, that before I had al finiſhed this my litle trauaile, the papiſte that I here ſpeake of, who chalenged me, and ranne againſt me at the tilte, though his place remained, was no where founde. Seing than that he was conueyghed out of the nature of thinges, thorough goddes goodnes, I thought it ſhuld be hurteful to noman, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to manie, if I went foreward with my matter begonne, and if I ſhuld publiſhe it to the world, whereof I had deliuered par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to the printer before. Further thou ſhalt vndreſtand, that theſe godlie men, whoſe names here folow, with certaine other, not only ſubſcribed with theyr awne handes to the doctrine, which I haue here ſette forth, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confirmed the ſame with ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; pithie argumen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes written by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſente in a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre to the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſte now
<pb facs="tcp:26558:32"/> departed, and gon out of the world.</p>
               <p>Theſe be their names.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>¶ M. Roger Parker.</item>
                  <item>¶ M. Iohan. Turnor.</item>
                  <item>¶ M. Doctor Perkins.</item>
                  <item>¶ M. Thomas Roſe.</item>
                  <item>¶ M. Gilbert Barckley.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Of theſe the firſt two be verie godlie gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle men, and wel trained in goddes worde. The other three haue ben lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge faithful mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of goddes word, &amp; be al men right worthie to be reuerenced, not o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly for their honorable age, and graye heares, but alſo much more for their feruent zeale towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des tru religion, and for their great graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and ſinceritee of life.</p>
               <p>After this M. Robert Watſon a wittie man longe exerciſed in matters of diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, &amp; able to ioigne in diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the popes bande in their cheife fild of glorie, &amp; where thei moſt approche the altar, though he were not preſent at the firſt ſubſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:33"/> yet afterwarde being talked withal, and required to ſhew his iudgment, ſubſcribed, with theſe wordes:</p>
               <q>IT VVAS GODDES VVIL, AND OR<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>DINANCE, VVILLINGLY TO SVF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FRE ADAM TO SINNE, VVHICH SINNE GOD OF HIS OMNIPOTENT POVVER TVRNED TO HIS GLORIE.
<bibl>¶ BY ME RO. VVATSON.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>In this ſhorte ſentence M. Watſon hath declared, that god ſuffred Adam to ſinne, not as one that wold not meddle with the matter, nor bend to anie parte, but as one that had willed, and ordained, that ſinne to be don. And therefore he thought it not enough, to ſaie, that it was goddes wil, but he wold adde moreouer, that it was god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ordinance, and that willingly, bicauſe he ſo purpoſed of him ſelfe, and bicauſe it ſemed ſo good to his aeternal wiſedom. And that noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore ſhuld impute the fault of Adams fal to god, ne make god the autor, or propre worcker of ſinne, he wold ſignifie by this word (to ſuffre) that albeit
<pb facs="tcp:26558:33"/> that it was goddes wil, and ordinance, that Adam ſhuld ſinne, yet god wrought not A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dams ſinne, but in ſuffring ordained it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his wil to be wrought thorough the enuie of the diuel, and Adams awne faulte, as M. Watſon than plainly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; as you maie finde ſufficiently taught in my expoſition vpon a parte of the 4. cha. of S. Io. reuel. and in the later ende of my former aunſwer to certaine ſophiſtical ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillations. Certaine other alſo verie god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie men, and verie worthie to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, ſubſcribed to this our ſentence, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe names in conſideration of their trauaile abrode in the middeſt of this croked gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, I thought not good to expreſſe in this place. Finally the hole companie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to this doctrine, that I haue here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and publiſhed, excepte one perſon only, which ſtode as a neuter, nether co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning, nor approuing either parte. And in dede amonge al other, he was of leſt eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. To god almightie therefore, who thorough his gratious goodnes vouch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſafed to open this truth vnto vs, to the gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at conforte, and ſtaie of our weake afflicted mindes in this woful tyme, and hath giuen vs a commune conſente therein, be al glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb facs="tcp:26558:34"/> and praiſe for euer. Amen amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <q>
                  <bibl>S. Aug. in the firſt boke of the predeſt. of ſainctes cha, 16.</bibl> It is tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the power of nawghtie men to ſinne. But that in ſinning the ſame nawgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines ſhal do this, or this, it is not in theyr power, but in the power of god, who diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth darcknes, &amp; ordreth it, that of this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that thei do againſt goddes wil, there is nothing fulfilled but goddes wil.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>S. Aug. in the bo. of free wil and grace cha. 20.</bibl> Which holie ſcripture, if it be diligently loked in to, ſheweth that not only the good willes of men, which he made of euil willes, and beinge made good by him guideth to good actes, but alſo thoſe willes that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the creation of the world, be ſo in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des power, that he maketh them to be bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whither he wil, and whan he wil, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to do good to ſome, or to puniſſh ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, as he him ſelfe declareth by his moſt hidden in dede, but vndoubtedly moſt iuſt iudgement. For we finde ſome ſinnes to be puniſhementes euen of other
<pb facs="tcp:26558:34"/> ſinnes. As is the hardening of Pharao, the cauſe whereof is alſo declared, to ſhew godddes power in him. Wherefore the lord ſaieth to Ioſue: The children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el ſhal not be able to ſtande. What is this, thei ſhal not be able to ſtand? Why did thei not ſtand by their fre wil, but fled their wil being trobled thorough feare, ſauing that god ruleth ouer the willes of men, &amp; whan he is angrie, turneth whom he wil in to fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re? Did not the ſhameles man, the ſonne of Iemini raile vpon kinge Dauid by his aw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne wil? Neuertheles what ſaieth Dauid? Suffre him to raile, for the lord hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded him to raile vpon Dauid. Lo how it is proued, that god vſeth the hertes euen of euil men, to the praiſe, and aide of good men.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>In the ſame bo. cha. 31.</bibl> Who ſhuld not tremble at theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of god, whereby he worketh euen in the hertes of euil men whatſoeuer he wil, rendring yet to them according to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertes. And againe: By theſe &amp; ſuch teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the holie ſcripture, it is made ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt enough, that god worcketh in the her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of men, to bow their willes whither ſo
<pb facs="tcp:26558:35"/> euer he wil, ether to good thinges accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his mercie, or to euil according to their deſertes, thorough his awne iudgement without doubte ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times open, ſometimes hidden, but euer iuſt.</q>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶CESSENT SOLITA</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device with a farmer or agricultural worker labelled "SAT QVERCVS" standing between a wheatfield with a crucifix at the center labelled "VERITAS" and a tree entwined by a serpent labelled "VMBRA"</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶DVM MELIORA.</p>
            <p>¶AN. DOMINI M.D.LVIII</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
